American Philosophical Society Archives. Record Group IIa. 1743-1806 APS.Archives.IIa APS.Archives.IIa
American Philosophical Society
- Papers
  - Report of the committee to whom was referred the essay on terrestrial magnetism, with the accompanying letter from the author, Mr. [Jean Baptiste] Biot, , 1805; 7 7/8" x 12 1/4"; American Philosophical Society
    [Philadelphia], ----, 4 pp. A.D.S.: R[obert] Patterson. Suggests experiments to check the accuracy of Mr. Biot's theory. Mentions T.Jefferson. FILM 199 FRAME 351
  - Report of the committee appointed to examine and report the most convenient situation for placing the skeleton of the elephant, January 17, 1806; 7 3/4" x 12 5/8"; American Philosophical Society
    [Philadelphia], 1 p. and endorsement. D.S.: J[oh]n Vaughan, Tho[mas] C. James. See Pro., XXII, pt. 3, 381.
  - Report of the committee to whom were referred the heads of two animals presented by D. S. Brown of Kentucky, January 17, 1806; 7 7/8" x 9 7/8"; American Philosophical Society
    [Philadelphia], 3 pp. and endorsement. A.D.S.: C[aspar] Wistar. jr. Heads identified as those of a bear and a wild musk hog.
  - The Insurance Company of North America to John Vaughan, January 18, 1806; 5 1/4" x 7 7/8"; Insurance Company of North America
    Treasurer of A.P.S. [Philadelphia], 1p. and endorsement D.S.: Cha[rle]s P. Heath. Receipt for $16, for insurance on Philosophical Hall and library for the year 1806.
  - Letter to Thos. T. Hewson, Jan. 21, 1806; 8" x 10"; Jefferson, Thomas, pres. U.S., 1743-1826
    Washington, A.L.S. 1p. and end. Acknowledges re-election as president of the A.P.S. Sends a paper from Dr. Sam. Brown on the salt-petre caves...of the western country. Bur. of rolls, v.6,215-S.1, v.11,109. FILM 199 FRAME 173
  - T[albot] Hamilton to John Vaughan, January 31, 1806; 7 1/8" x 9 1/8"; Hamilton, Talbot
    Philadelphia, 2 pp., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Presents to the A.P.S. a book (not named) in return for one or more duplicates of some old almanacs purchased by the A.P.S. at the sale of [Benjamin] Franklin's library. FILM54-64 FRAME124
  - William Read to Thomas Jefferson, February 11, 1806; 7 3/4" x 9 5/8"; Read, William, 1754-1845
    Charleston, S. C., 1 p. and endorsement. A.L.S. Presents two fossils to Mr. Jefferson. FILM 199 FRAME 120
  - Letter to Mr. Destutt-Tracy, 1806 Feb. 14; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826
    Jefferson thanks Destutt-Tracy for sending him portions of his work on ideology.
  - Report of committee on Henri Peyrouse's memoir on the columns of Hercules, March 7, 1806; 7x8; American Philosophical Society
    D.S.: B.S.Barton, Peter S.DuPonceau and Sam. B. Wylie. 1p.and end. Cf. Minutes, p.383.
  - Report of committee on the deltas of the Mississippi and the Nile by Henri Peyrouse, March 7, 1806; 6x8; American Philosophical Society
    D.S.: Nichol. Collin, Zaccheus Collins and C. Wistar, jr. 1p. and end. Cf. Minutes, p. 383.
  - Rob[ert] R. Livingston to John Vaughan, Librarian of A.P.S., March 9, 1806; 7 7/8" x 10 1/8"; Livingston, Robert R., 1746-1813
    Clermont, N. Y., 5 pp. address and endorsement A.L.S. Regarding lavas sent from Naples to the A.P.S. See Minutes, April 4 1806, in Pro., XXII, pt. 3, 384.
  - Report of committee on [Samuel) Brown's memoir on salt-petre caves in Kentucky, March 21, 1806; 6x8; American Philosophical Society
    D.S.: A. Fothergill and Adam seybert. 1p.and end. Cf. Minutes, p.384. Printed: Trans. ,o.s. ,vol.VI, 235 ff. For map, see: Brown,S. Map...; [read) Feb. 7,805.
  - American Philos[ophical] Soc[iet]y to John Wainwright, March 22, 1806; 3 3/4" x 7 1/4"; American Philosophical Society
    Dr., Philadelphia, 1 p. and endorsement. D. Receipted by John Wainwright. Receipted bill for $8, for altering the fireplace in Philosophical Hall.
  - Th[omas] Jefferson to [John] Vaughan, March 25, 1806; 7 15/16" x 9 3/4"; Jefferson, Thomas, pres. U.S., 1743-1826
    Washington, 1 p. and endorsement. A.L.S. Sends to the A.P.S. "a copy of my communications to Congress of the information respecting Louisiana.. ." Microfilmed - Film 199,89
  - Letter to [Thomas Jefferson]; the President of the A.P.S., March 25, 1806; 10x8; Tatham, William, 1752-1819
    Washington, A.L.S. 7p.and end. Concerning the tomb of Ferdinand Columbus at Seville, together with translation of the inscription. Enclosed originally in: Jefferson to Wistar; March 26, 1806. Film 199-403 Frame 6-352
  - Report of the committee to whom was referred DR. [Samuel L.] Mitchell's paper on the subject of ice-islands, April 4, 1806; 7 3/8" x 9 11/16"; American Philosophical Society
    [Philadelphia], 1 p. and endorsement. D.S.: R[obert] Patterson, B[enjamin] S[mith] Bartom, A[nthony] Fothergill. Do not recommend publication.
  - [L. P. F. de] Beaujour to [John] Vaughan, April 4, 1806; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Beaujour, Louis Philippe Felix de
    Philadelphia, 1 p. and endorsement. 3d. per. N. (In French.) Presents to the A.P.S. his Tableau du commerce de la Grèce, 2 vols. See Pro., XXII, pt. 3, 384.
  - Christofe Rieder to B[enjamin] S[mith] Barton, April 10, 1806; 3 3/4" x 7 7/8"; Rieder, Christofe
    Philadelphia, 1 p. and endorsement. D.S. Receipt for $10, for drawing of spined lizard.
  - John Vaughan to James Howell and Company, April 11, 1806; 4 5/8" x 7 7/8"; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
    Dr., Philadelphia, 1 p. and endorsement. D. Receipted by James Howell & Co. Receipted bill for $154.28, for three gold medals for Magellanic awards.
  - John Vaughan to James Howell and Company, April 23, 1806; 3 7/8" x 7 3/4"; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
    Dr., Philadelphia, 1 p. and endorsement. D. Receipted by James Howell & Co. Receipted bill for $45.38, for one gold medal for Magellanic award.
  - G. Baron to Jno. Vaughan, April 25, 1806; 7 7/8" x 9 3/4"; Baron, George
    New York, 1 P., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Intends to be in Philadelphia the first week in June, at which time he desires to communicate to the A.P.S. his views upon a new system of navigation. See Pro., XXII, pt. 3, 385.
  - Report of committee on [Anthony] Fothergill's paper on icebergs, May 2, 1806; 9-1/2x7-1/2; American Philosophical Society
    D.S.: R.Patterson, Tho[mas] C.James and Tho[ma]s T.Hewson. 2p.,end. Cf. Minutes, p.385.
  - Report of the committee to whom was referred the communication by W[illia]m Tatham of facsimile of the tomb of Ferdinand Columbus, May 2, 1806; 9" x 7 13/16"; American Philosophical Society
    Philadelphia, 2 pp. D.S.: B[enjamin] S[mith] Barton, J[oh]n Vaughan, W[illia]m Tilghman.
  - Th[omas] Jefferson to [John] Vaughan, May 4, 1806; 7 7/8" x 9 13/16"; Jefferson, Thomas, pres. U.S., 1743-1826
    Washington, 1 p. and endorsement. A.L.S. Sends to the A.P.S. a box of minerals from Captain [Meriwether] Lewis and a bathometer invented by Mr. Luiscius. Microfilmed - Film 199,90
  - Edward Miller to John Vaughan, May 5, 1806; 8" x 10"; Miller, Edward, 1760-1812
    New York, 1 p., address and endorsement. 3d. per. N. Presents to Mr. Vaughan -- copies of the report to Governor Lewis relative to yellow fever.
  - Report of the committee appointed to examine the treasurer's accounts, May 15, 1806; 5 5/8" x 7 5/8"; American Philosophical Society
    Philadelphia, 1 p. and endorsement. D.S.: R[obert] Patterson, Joseph Cloud.
  - The American Philos[ophical] Soc[iet]y to F. R. Hassler, May 16, 1806; 8 1/8" x 9"; American Philosophical Society
    Dr., Philadelphia, 1 p. and endorsement. D. Receipted by F. R. Hassler. Receipted bill for $12, for Connaissance des temps.
  - Letter to ---- ----, May 30, 1806; 7 1/2" x 4 1/4"; Niemcewicz, Julian Ursyn, 1758-1841
    A.L.S. 1p. Etymology of the word Stanislaus. FILM 403 FRAME 75
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Philadelphia, May 31, 1806; 9x7-1/2; Branger, Meynts & Co.
    Amsterdam, L. 1p.and add.,end. "Duplicate." Has not received the seeds from the APS for the Haarlem society.
  - And[re]w Ellicott to John Vaughan, June 18, 1806; 6 5/8" x 8 1/8"; Ellicott, Andrew, 1754-1820
    Lancaster, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Forwards the first volume of the measure of the meridian in France as a present from [J. B. J.] Delambre to the A.P.S.
  - Th[omas] Jefferson to [Caspar] Wistar, June 20, 1806; 7 7/8" x 9 7/8"; Jefferson, Thomas, pres. U.S., 1743-1826
    Washington, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Donates some coins and medals to the A.P.S. See Minutes, July 18, 1806, in Pro., XXII, pt. 3, 387. Microfilmed- Film 199,91
  - John C. Kunze to Robert Patterson, June 25, 1806; 7 11/16" x 9 15/16"; Kunze, John C. (John Christopher), 1744-1807
    New York, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Sends to Mr. Patterson three copies of his pamphlet upon the eclipse of June 16, 1806. See Pro., XXII, pt. 3, 388. Mentions T.Jefferson. FILM 199 FRAME 353
  - The Am[erica]n Philos[ophical] Soc[iet]y to F. R. Hassler, July 5, 1806; 7 1/8" x 9 3/8"; American Philosophical Society
    Dr., Philadelphia, 1 p. and endorsement. D. Receipted by F. R. Hassler. Receipted bill for $129, for 51 volumes of French scientific journals.
  - F. R. Hassler to John Vaughan, Treasurer of A.P.S., July 12, 1806; 4" x 8"; Hassler, F. R. (Ferdinand Rudolph), 1770-1843
    Philadelphia, 1 p. and endorsement. A.D.S. Receipt for $17, for designated books purchased by the American Philosophical Society.
  - Letter to Robert Patterson, Philadelphia, July 17, 1806; 9-1/2x7-1/2; Garnett, John
    New Brunswick, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Math.and astronomy, vol. 2, no. 56.) Method of finding altitudes, etc.
  - American Philos[ophical] Soc[iet]y to John Wainwright,Dr., Philadelphia, July 28, 1806; 5 1/2" x 7 1/2"; American Philosophical Society
    1 p. and endorsement. D. Receipted by John Wainwright. Receipted bill for $6.50, for carpentry work at the Rittenhouse Observatory.
  - The American Philosophical Society to Tho[ma]s P. Jones, July 30, 1806; 3 3/4" x 7 7/8"; American Philosophical Society
    Dr., [Philadelphia], 1 p. and endorsement. D. Receipted by Tho[ma]s P. Jones. Receipted bill for $4, for four boxes for Magellanic premium medals.
  - The American Philo[sophica]l Society to Jacob Lybrand, August 1, 1806; 6 1/4" x 8 1/8"; American Philosophical Society
    Dr., [Philadelphia], 1 p. and endorsement. D. Receipted by Jacob Lybrand. Receipted bill for $35.28, for carpentry work at the Rittenhouse Observatory.
  - Report of committee on [Anthony] Fothergill's paper on bills of mortality for the U.S., Aug. 15, 1806; 4x8; American Philosophical Society
    D.S.: Nich.Collin, Z. Collins and James. 1p.and end. Cf. Minutes, p.387.
  - Report of committee on Sam[ue]l F. Conover's paper on blood, Aug. 15, 1806; 5-1/2x9-1/2; American Philosophical Society
    D.S.: R. Patterson, J. Mease and Adam Seybert. 1p.and end. Cf. Minutes, p.387. Printed: Trans.,o.s.,vol.VI, 247 ff. For original paper, see: Conover. Concerning...blood; June 10, 1806.
  - Concerning the solar eclipse of June 16, 1806, Aug. 15, 1806; 8x5; Dunbar, William, 1749-1810
    [read] A.D.S. 8p.,end. (see Ms.comm. to the APS. Math.and astronomy, vol. 2, no. 62.) ----Copy, 7p.and end. Cf. Minutes, p.388. Printed: Trans o.s., vol. VI, 260 ff.
  - Philad[elphi]a [sic] Philosophical Society to George Flake, August 16, 1806; 3 1/2" x 8"; American Philosophical Society
    Dr., Philadelphia, 1 p. and endorsement. D. Receipted George Flake. Receipted bill for £2.12.6, for painting done at the Rittenhouse Observatory.
  - Talbot Hamilton to John Vaughan, September 6, 1806; 7 1/2" x 9 1/2"; Hamilton, Talbot
    Philadelphia, 2 pp., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Donates piece of a loadstone from Schuyler's Mountain to A.P.S. See Minutes, September 19, 1806, in Pro., XXII, pt. 3, 389.
  - The American Philo[sophica]l Society to Jacob Lybrand, September 8, 1806; 6 1/4" x 8 1/8"; American Philosophical Society
    Dr., [Philadelphia], 1 p. and endorsement. D. Receipted by Jacob Lybrand. Receipted bill for $12.83, for making set of inside shutters for Philosophical Hall.
  - The American Philosophical Society to F. R. Hassler, September 12, 1806; 4" x 7 1/2"; American Philosophical Society
    Dr., 1 p. and endorsement. D. Receipted by F. R. Hassler. Receipted bill for $10, for René Just Haüy, Traité de minéralogie, 5v.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Sept. 16, 1806; 10x8; Foronda, Valentín, 1751-1821
    Philadelphia, L.S. 10p.and end. In Spanish. (see Ms.Comm.to the APS. Medicine, anatomy and physiology, no. 31.) Concerning Lafuente's method of curing yellow fever. Cf. Minutes, pp.389, 391.
  - Report of committee on [Anthony] Fothergill's paper on population, Sept. 19, 1806; 5-1/2x6; American Philosophical Society
    D.S.: Nich.Collin, Tho. C. James, and Zaccheus Collins. 1p.and end. Cf. Minutes, p.388.
  - Report of committee on C[harles] W[illson] Peale's description of an American antelope, Sept. 19, 1806; 6-1/2x8; American Philosophical Society
    D.S.: B.S. Barton. 1p.and end. Cf. Minutes, p.388.
  - Concerning the cure of yellow fever, Sept. 19, 1806; Foronda, Valentín, 1751-1821
    [presented] D. 13p.and end. In Spanish. 10c8. (see Ms.Comm.to the APS. Medicine, anatomy and physiology, no.26.) Cf. Minutes, p.389.
  - Am[erica]n Philos[ophical] Soc[iet]y to Geo[rge] Flake, September 24, 1806; 3 3/4" x 8 1/8"; American Philosophical Society
    Dr., [Philadelphia], 1 p. and endorsement. D. Receipted by George Flake. Receipted bill for painting and plastering.
  - Letter to ----, Sept. 30, 1806; 13-1/2x8-1/2; Hassler, F. R. (Ferdinand Rudolph), 1770-1843
    Switzerland, L. Extract. 3p.and end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Philology, literature, etc., vol. 1, no. 21.) Concerning a landslide.
  - Report of committee on papers on the eclipse by Ellicott and Dunbar, and Dunbar's paper on ascertaining longitude, Oct. 3, 1806; 6x8; American Philosophical Society
    D.S.: Ferrer and R.Patterson. 1p.and end. Cf. Minutes, p.389. Printed: Trans.,o.s.,vol.VI, 260ff. For Ellicott's paper, see:letter from Ellicott to R.Patterson;Aug.1,1806.
  - Report of the committee to whom was referred Dr. [Anthony] Fotghergill's memoir on ice islands, October 3, 1806; 7 1/2" x 9 3/4"; American Philosophical Society
    Philadelphia, 1 p. and endorsement. D.S.: Peter S. DuPonceau, Joseph Cloud, Sam[ue]l Moore. Publication not recommended, as anthor paper on the same subject is at present before the public.
  - Letter to J.R. Coxe, secretary of the APS, Oct. 23, 1806; 7 1/4" x 9"; Asiatic Society of Bengal
    Calcutta, L.S: Wm. Hunter. secy. 1p. and end. Acknowledges books from APS.
  - W[illiam] Jones to John Vaughan, December 4, 1806; 4 3/4" x 7 3/4"; Jones, William, of Calcutta
    Philadelphia, 1 p., address and endorsement. 3d. per. N. Presents five books of Chinese paintings of natural subjects to the A.P.S. See Minutes, December 5, 1806, in Pro. XXII, pt. 3, 391.
  - Report of committee on [John] Hall's paper on navigation, Dec. 5, 1806; 5-1/2x8; American Philosophical Society
    D.S.: R.Patterson and James Mease. 1p. Cf. Minutes, p.391.
  - Report of committee on [José Joaquin] de Ferrer's paper on the eclipse, Dec. 5, 1806; 6-1/2x8; American Philosophical Society
    D.S.: Joseph Clay and R.Patterson. 1p. and end. Cf. Minutes, p.391. Printed: Trans.,o.s.,vol.VI, 264,293.
  - Report of committee on Guyton [de] Morveau's paper on disinfecting the air, Dec. 5, 1806; 10x8; American Philosophical Society
    D.S.: Tho.C.James, Thos.T.Hewson and Jos.Cloud. 1p.and end. Refers to Jefferson. Cf. Minutes, p.391.
  - Hu[gh] Williamson to James Mease, December 9, 1806; 7 13/16" x 9 13/16"; Williamson, Hugh, 1735-1819
    Philadelphia, 1 p. and endorsement. A.L.S. Desires to have a copy of his paper on the fascination of serpents, in order to make additions thereto.
  - Report of the committee appointed to examine the treasurer's accounts, December 31, 1806; 5 5/16" x 7 3/4"; American Philosophical Society
    [Philadelphia], 1 p. and endorsement. D.S.: R[obert] Patterson, Joseph Cloud.